Okay, so in this video, we're
going to talk about another
tool-in technique called
Schedule compression, right?
Schedule compression techniques.
Now, scheduled compression
is considered a tool and
technique, right, from the
old pinbox 6, right, standard.
So they have scheduled
compression techniques was one
of the tools and techniques
of developed schedule.
Now, there are two types of schedule
compression techniques, something called
crashing and the other one called fast
tracking.
Now, first of all, let's
actually talk about
what do we mean by schedule compression.
I mean, as the name suggests, compression
reducing the schedule.
So let's say we go behind schedule,
right, we're going behind schedule.
And so the remaining schedule
now we want to try and compress
it, try and reduce the schedule
so that we can finish on time.
So that's what schedule compression refers
to.
Now there's two times, crashing and fast
tracking.
Now, let's talk about this first one,
crashing.
Crashing specifically means adding
additional resources.
And you're adding additional resources to
critical path activities.
So whenever you hear the term,
we have to crash the schedule.
Whenever you hear that
term crashing the schedule,
it always refers to adding
additional resources.
So whether there are additional team
members or additional machines,
additional raw materials, or whatever it
is, are you adding additional resources?
But you're adding them to critical path
activities.
Not to non-critical path
activities, non-critical
path activities can be delayed anyway.
So if an activity that can have float,
if that gets delayed, that's not going to
delay the project, but
if a critical path activity
is delayed, that's a
delay on the whole project.
So you're adding additional resources to
critical path activities.
Whether you're adding people or
whether you're adding machines,
well, what effect is that
going to have on your project?
Think about that.
What effect is that going to have?
You're adding more people, you're adding
more machines.
That's going to increase cost.
The biggest effect is your cost is going
to increase.
That's a main effect.
Now, it can also increase risk,
but the main effect is to increase cost.
So, even say we want to bring in a
machine, right, well, we want to bring in
an extra machine, that's going to cost
money, but then we might need to bring in
some additional labour to utilise that
machine.
Again, that's going to cost more money,
right?
So crashing is always going to have the
effect of increasing cost.
It can increase risk, main effect is to
increase cost.
So, from an example perspective,
right, you are going to choose crashing
when you have the funds
for crashing, right, when
you have the funds to
increase additional resources.
So let's say you've got
a situation where you're
going behind schedule,
but then you're under budget.
Well, you've got some
additional funds that are under
budget, so crashing might
be an option there, right?
Or let's say senior management or your
customer has approved
some additional funding.
Again, crashing would be an option there.
Now, crashing also is not just a
free-for-all.
Oh, let's bring in anyone and everyone.
No, again, remember,
doubling the number of resources
is not going to halve the
time in which to do the work.
So you're going to crash, you're going to
bring in resources incrementally at the
most incrementally efficient, you know,
cost.
So that's crashing.
Another tool then is this one called fast
tracking.
And fast tracking means
items that you'd plan to run
sequentially, you're now
going to run them in parallel.
So you're converting sequential items into
parallel.
And the main effect of that is to increase
risk.
That can also increase cost, but the main
effect is to increase risk.
Because now you had planned, you had
planned to finish this activity before you
start this next one, but now you're going
to do them in parallel, right?
So that can increase risk.
All right, so we first want
to paint the upstairs of the
house blue, then we'll paint
the downstairs of the house red.
But let's do them both in parallel now.
But we're going a little behind schedule.
We'll do them both at the same time.
Well, we might end up mixing the colors
together, right?
Or, you know, some rooms upstairs will end
up painting red instead of blue and some
rooms downstairs,
we'll, you know, again, we
might end up painting
them the wrong colour.
This is a very, very simple example.
So the main effect of fast tracking is
going to increase risk.
Now, also understand something very,
very important here.
Fast tracking, you can all do fast tracking
if you have a discretionary dependency.
Remember, discretionary dependency.
It's up to us.
We can move activities around as opposed
to mandatory dependency.
If it's a mandatory dependency.
We won't be able to move them around.
So as a simple example, building a house,
right?
We have to dig the foundations.
We have to finish digging
the foundations before we can
start framing, before we
can start putting up the walls.
Right, we can't decide as we're digging
the foundations.
You know what?
Let's just do this in parallel now.
We'll, you know, we're going a little
behind a schedule.
So let's, as we're digging the
foundations, once we start digging the
foundations, then we can start putting up
the walls.
No.
You have to finish.
digging the foundations before you can
start framing.
So that would be a mandatory
dependency, in which
case, fast tracking will
not be a viable option.
It's only if it's a discretionary.
So for example, quality control versus
user acceptance testing.
We want to test the product first.
We as a team.
We want to finish quality control.
We want to finish
testing the product before
we give it to the
customer for their testing.
for their user acceptance testing.
Ideally, we'd like to do that.
So we've planned quality control first,
user acceptance testing afterwards.
However, if we're running a little behind
schedule, there's no reason why,
you know, the customer
can't start their testing
while we're still
finishing up our testing.
So we can convert now these two sequential
items into parallel.
Because at that point, that's a
discretionary dependency.
There's nothing saying that we have to
test it first before the customer test it,
or rather there's nothing
saying that we have to
complete testing before
the customer can test it.
So that's a discretionary dependency and
therefore we can fast track.
All right.
So these are the two types
of scheduled compression
techniques are crashing and fast tracking.